hello everyone it's april 25th 2022
we're here with adam saffron and today
we're going to be having a guest stream
the radically embodied conscious
cybernetic bayesian brain from free
energy to free will and back again so
adam thanks a ton for joining on this
day really looking forward to your
presentation and thanks again adam take
it away
uh thank you for inviting me and um or
letting me come to talk with you and
see i'll present some ideas from a
uh recent manuscript in
entropy called the radically embodied
conscious cybernetic bayesian brain
from free will from free energy to free
will and back again
and after that looking forward to
discussing some of the ideas with all of
you and um
hopefully this is the beginning of an
ongoing conversation
so what i tried to do with this
manuscript was
basically um
marry
good old-fashioned cognitive science
with a more an activist perspective
trying to find a middle way between
these ways of viewing of things and this
is the view that i've come to over a
number of years where um the idea being
that embodiment like
at this point you know it's not news
that the mind is embodied
but uh the claim is that it is uh very
very embodied some would say radically
embodied um i'm not sure if that made
the most sense to use that term because
the term radical with respect to
embodiment
is usually pointing to a perspective
or radical in activism
that avoids talking about
representations or models and instead of
saying you know what's really going on
is these couplings of the world and
maybe you can say there's like an
implicit information processing or
intelligence even that might be objected
to but
we talk of representations and
symbols and models from cognitive
science um that's
those are
not real things
and so this paper goes through a
perspective in which basically
um
we do uh have representations and models
and we also have um
these sort of inactive couplings with
the world
um and i say it's radical and that uh
nearly uh every mental process you would
care to talk about the way you have to
understand it
according to this view would be
first and fundamentally and foremost in
terms of its embodied character
so
before i move on as everything coming
across clearly uh just
okay
yeah i did disable my video because due
to some incredible consequences of
different situations i'm using a hotspot
but it's all good
okay
you're on the run
um
so
let's review a little background i mean
a lot of this um uh
people who were watching this
with but i'll review some uh background
on predictive processing and uh active
inference um
maybe some of what i'll
present is a somewhat heterodox view
that's also something to discuss
so a basic account of predictive coding
you have these
deep
pyramidal neurons and you have these
superficial pyramidal neurons
where they're deep with respect to
cortex as having this layered structure
roughly six layers with some variations
on the theme depending on where you look
and the idea is that
the cortex as a whole
is engaging in
what's sometimes called hierarchical or
what's often called hierarchical
predictive coding or
potentially predictive processing
because there might be some assumptions
with saying predictive coding that not
everyone would sign up for such as that
um
you are only suppressing and explaining
away information as opposed to
um
sometimes enhancing it
and there's other nuances that could
make people object to saying predictive
coding
instead of getting into those weeds uh
the idea would be that you have this
hierarchy of beliefs
implicit and neuronal organization um
the nature of these beliefs and this
gets into these
debates about representation and
inactivism but this idea that
you can say there's an implicit belief
at each
neuron and set of neurons about what
they expect what patterns they expect to
encounter and according to this
predictive processing view
through their activity they're trying to
predict this incoming activity and
suppress it or explain it away
to minimize overall activity
and you that you only update these
beliefs where you got it wrong via a
prediction error and this is a
under certain certain assumptions if you
have a good model and events in the
world are relatively slow relative to
your internal signaling units you can
have substantial energetic savings for
an organ of about two percent of your
body mass and 20 of your metabolism
seems like the kind of thing natural
selection would do and there's some
decent evidence for this
so
this
so the basics of neural architecture
here for cortex is viewing it as a
predictive processing hierarchy or a
header
and that each of your modalities would
be a different belief hierarchy and they
would all
come together and exchange their
information for a joint belief
across all your modalities in terms of
what you think um should be in your
sensorium as it moves through the world
uh whether it's the world you're in
right now or some sort of counterfactual
world in the present or future
so that's predictive processing in a
nutshell
and so in this account the goal was to
use
predictive processing to
try to get into the micro mechanics of
goal-oriented behavior and agency
and so what i suggested is that um the
work has been done within active
inference um
on this sort of
imaginative plan
pursuing of goals
the work to refer to would be
sophisticated inference or sophisticated
affect of inference which is
thinking about basically planning into
the future as this tree search of
possibilities where you're going on
different
branches of these possibilities and then
picking the ones either in imagination
or in reality that would correspond to
you
minimizing your prediction error the
best or realizing value the best
but
this exploration of a tree of
possibilities and going down different
branches
and so this would be i suppose a
particular flavor of this and the idea
being that um a lot of what would be
pulling along this stream of
consciousness of imaginings um
would be this iterative comparison
between
sensed and imagined states or between
various goal states
so here um i
have this comic book that a friend
helped me make
and
i have multiple comics throughout i tend
to view comics as being
really
highly expressive in a way that um i
think we should probably use them more
in terms of being able to capture the
the joints and experience space with
sufficient richness and detail and there
could even be something like comic
book-esque about the stream of
experience which could be part of the
reason that they're so effective
but to return to this
comic or a modal frame sequence as i
sometimes call it
um you see in the bottom here this is
the actual pose of the agent and up top
what's going through the mind's eye
whether we're talking about an
imagination or a perception and so here
it's just a simple contrasting of what
you're perceiving in each given moment
and then what you're imagining so you're
sitting you want tea
you
then look and you say i'm not drinking
tea i'm at my computer and there's a
laptop in front of me
you look down
and you're imagining having tea in your
cup but then you look and no there is
indeed no t
and then you imagine a next step and so
what's what's happening here is you're
doing this contrast and what i propose
is that in contrast between these states
they're arranging they're basically
setting up prediction errors for each
other where what doesn't match
would potentially
get you a natural prioritization
of
what features are unaligned and then
from those you use that to retrieve some
sort of relevant affordance to help you
bridge this gap between your imagination
reality and there's a lot of devils in
details of the ways this could work but
that some sort of iterative contrasting
of
um
goal states in a goal hierarchy where
it's like you might have an ultimate
goal but to achieve that goal you have
to now go and think of what are all of
the sub steps and the sub goals that
would be needed to actually get the tea
in my hand
you're going to have to
ambulate to the kitchen make the tea etc
etc
and as you're going back and forth at
some place some point you either have a
plan that's compelling enough or the
next action is close enough to your
present pose that you just find yourself
launching into action sometimes
accompanied by a feeling of having
decided sometimes you just find yourself
moving but that's the basic um account
here that
the stream of consciousness is being
pulled along in this goal-oriented
fashion
this value-driven fashion um sometimes
more freely wandering but sometimes but
but usually there's an interest and
you're as an active inference and
predictive processing
your
preferences or your attracting states
the tractors that you'll find as a
system which you're attracted to
takes the form of predictions and so the
things in your mind that you're
imagining
that
they become the goal state they become
the state of the world that you prefer
in that instance or in general if it's a
regular kind of imagining and this now
becomes the attracting state that your
system self organizes and
you engage in action selection of
different kinds to
minimize that difference between what
you're imagining
and what
you are estimating for the world
so
um i go into some discussion of uh
neural architecture and different
aspects that might be more or less
relevant for different um
of this kind of action selection um i
probably should have just you know
thrown this on top of a picture of a
brain um but i didn't but in some ways
it might be a good thing and that
i wonder whether
this account of having a dual-tier
system something like uh a system in a
system two
is a broader story than just brains and
so you know i have written out here like
here would be neural substrates of what
would enable you to do this
but um well it could be across brains
you might have similar processes
happening
within let's say like an insect nervous
system by different means like instead
of the basal ganglia you might be using
the mushroom bodies um if we're talking
like an ant colony for instance it's
possible you have a different like
attracting states of the colony where
some are taking this role like a higher
level controller and a lower level
controller but the basic idea here is
that you have an upper level controller
that's capable of aggregating
information across different so you have
this lower level process by in this
control hierarchy where the lower level
is
taking care of your immediate couplings
with the world this would be um the more
inactive portion um if we're talking
about the brain it would be something
like um
loosely assembled
um constellation of
um
cortical reactive dispositions may be
orchestrated by the cerebellar system
of what would be called amortized
inference and it would be largely
unconscious and automatic um
phenomenologists would talk about just
like um things being
ready at hand as opposed to being
present to hand you're just effortless
engagement and effortless mastery with
the world
but on top of this um you would have a
slower process in this case i'm saying
it's more involving conscious processing
something more
system two-like to use kahneman's
language um where it's involved in more
deliberate
potentially effortful uh modes of
cognition which would be a higher level
of control over
this um
faster smooth coupling
system
so
go into some details of neural
architecture
potentially this might be just
what you need for a lot of active
inferential agents
something like this across
whether or not we're talking about
neurons this this might be a broader
story for um active inferential agents
so to return to the example um
of making tea uh you go into it
somewhere saying that um you know
areas associated with mental imagery
maybe even physical and computational
substrates of
mental imagery phenomenal phenomenality
itself but like the petunias for
instance um involved in imagination have
heavily implicated um multiple reasons
to think why this would be the case but
you know i have this little cartesian
theater here with the different
imaginings
and
down below the idea is you are
iterating through different imaginations
imaginings
largely via
large-scale orchestration by the
hippocampal complex and it's a
capacities
to
couple with the rest of cortex to
guide these
high-level attracting states
where some portions of which would be
your experience
and so the reason you would bring up the
hippocampus in here is it seems to be
a specialized subsystem for
sequential predictive modeling
you could say that for cortex as a whole
technically hippocampus is a kind of
cortex
arcade cortex old vintage but that
basically um so demacia will talk about
this in terms of a convergence
divergence zone where many things will
funnel in and then funnel back with high
centrality um
uh i forget his name he said waterloo um
the spawn architecture um but uh he'll
talk about semantic pointers but there's
different ways of viewing the this the
high centrality of the campus as it
basically
will
predict this trajectory of the overall
organism through space
you can both encode
memories what was happening in my
thorium whether in reality or
imagination at each point as i was
moving moving through space and time and
you could also use it for replay
including in counter factual
circumstances and so um i have some
diagrams here at the neural systems
involved
and right here you would have the
i think that's good for now so um
everyone wants to know more details
about that later we could
so
to return to um
trying to go more phenomenological um so
these modal frame sequences are comics
ultimately what i'm trying to build up
to
is a sufficiently detailed account of
neural architecture and a sufficiently
detailed account of phenomenology
that we can talk about
so that we can basically talk about
something as highfalutin as free will
and have some purchase
um
so in this a little more complex modal
form sequence you have that up top
an imagining you know
row below that you have what's actually
in your perception
below that you have your pose your
proprioceptive
imprints and then below that you have
your enteroceptive inference
and
so
as you're stepping through
the stream of consciousness is evolving
through space and time
encoded or orchestrated
by the hippocampal system at this high
potentially
most integrative high level of action
selection
you
are having
different wounds in your body
um
corresponding to the enteroceptive
competence of um or the interceptive
aspects of um what it means to be in
different situations so for instance
like a hunger situation here you're
getting prediction air intercepted
prediction air that would be um roughly
vaguely localized here's like a cool
sensation
um around your um gut and mouth or
thirst or hunger something like this and
now as you're going into movement you
might have here like um
you're still having this enteroceptive
code of hot and cold states pleasant and
unpleasant but it's kind of getting
infused into other other modalities
where your proprioception some of the
phenomenology of like feeling like an
urge in your body it's
one of the claims i make is that you
have this kind of
quasi-synesthetic cross-mapping between
enteroceptive signals signals
and the proprioceptive and exterceptive
asp um
their associates
uh part of the reason i claim this and
say that this is both part of the
phenomenology of will and maybe part of
the mechanism also um is that
interceptive signals um are poorly
localizable in space and time they tend
to have pretty low resolution for them
um
and so they
may drift free from their sources and as
a kind of anomalous inference but
adaptively adaptive anomalous inference
you they may get infused into
the relevant um effector and sensor
systems and objects in the worlds for
which um they would be relevant
you know i make a lot of different
claims in this work uh from a number of
years of study
a lot of it can be taken a la carte like
you can find some things to be more
compelling some things be less
compelling
but
i do think you get a whole lot greater
than some of its parts but it can also
be taken in a piecemeal fashion so you
might not be particularly compelled by
this
account of interception as being
synesthetic in nature um but
nothing really not too much will ride on
that but
it could
will write on that but it could end up
being important so i'm putting it in
there
okay
and so across all of this is happening
within a
perspective of computational
neurophenomenology
as a neil seth calls it or i call it
marion neurophenomenology and the reason
i call it marion is specifically
his account of multiple levels of
analysis
which
i guess super vein on each other and
you can do two things because things
have these multiple levels that they can
be engaged with um you can either engage
with them a la carte because of uh let's
say for instance you want to do
cognitive science but you have no idea
how the brain works and then
for many years we haven't and there's a
lot of mystery still you can kind of
bracket like here's this big set of
unknowns but it's at a different level
but working at this other level we can
obtain knowledge even though we might be
ignorant at these other levels
um and
that would be you know functionalism and
cognitive science but uh for me what's
more exciting about this actually this
marian stack
is the capacity not for independence but
interdependence and mutual constraints
using the implementational level or the
mechanistic level as a constraint of
what's a likely set of algorithms using
a likely set of algorithms to test
hypotheses on the implementation level
using what you think
the functions
things like neuropsychiatric literature
to constrain and then your imaging
literature to constrain algorithm and
thereby implementational so they the
idea of what excites me is like building
in this crossroad puzzle
constraints
and then cross-referencing them within
the phenomenon
level
i'm using basically machine learning as
a person principle and typically uh
going to the races of this idea that a
lot of cortex could be understood in
terms of historical
predictive problems uh but also evoking
some additional machine learning
principles but that's the overall uh
scope of it
in terms of the um
like all the body parts and faces this
is part of like the radical embodiment
idea is that instead of like the cortex
being this like grab bag of associations
with areas and
does that mean
um the idea is that once you really
place it front and center as a
cybernetic controller for an embodied
embedded agent once you place embodiment
front and center
wait a second that's not too many steps
removed from where the ears first pipe
in so the idea that something like
you know going from
phonemes or you know going from sound
patterns undifferentiated to phonemes
and
it ends up making cortex and its
functions in my opinion a lot more
applicable it becomes somewhat like
location location location and location
relative to the modalities that ends up
explaining a lot of things a similar
story for broca's area um what a
coincidence that it's not too many you
know it's a hop skip and a jump away
from what might uh move your mouth bits
um
there's doubles in details here right i
don't be glib and underestimated
complexity but
the claim is that actually once you
place embodiment in the center an
elegance kind of falls out and becomes a
lot easier to keep track of things if
you're thinking of cortex as this
control cybernetic control hierarchy
over to basically help a body move
through the world and model the world as
it moves through it
so we are ready i think to get to free
will um
and so taking these modal frame
sequences and here is doing one for this
experience of standing um
to make tea
and then
taking that model and then pouring it to
a bad experience so what is a little bit
paradigm um
so some people say le bay some people
say look back i think
that's deadlocked
but i'll continue to say well bacon is
more common
and i just will um
but the idea is that you're there and
you want to see do people or don't they
have something like meaningful
conscious control over their actions
and so the idea is okay let's strip this
down and take like the most
insignificant of all actions like well
surely we need to have control there um
if we're gonna say we have control
anymore and so the decision to just move
your hand based on feeling like you want
to do so um
and this coming from
basically it's endogenous you're not
being it's not being decided from
without but um you doing something based
on something internal to you
and what was found with these
um lebet's studies
or the bay is that you get this ramping
activity um
preceding
the decision to move your hand
so it's one more thing you have this
clock right
and there is
it's a big clock that you're looking at
and there might be a dot or a big hand
moving in a circle and the reason that
you have this is basically so that you
can estimate the time when it was that
you said i will move my hand when did
you decide
and you then say okay when you made that
decision what were you looking at where
was this dot as it moved around in a
circle and this can get you very fine
resolution um sub second resolution
because if it's a big clock that's
because then the dot will be moving
slowly and you can say okay it was right
there
but what's observed is that you're
getting this ramping activity with this
predictive of the action called the
readiness potential
and it will peak you know a good 200
milliseconds before you reporting it
varies but it'll peak substantially
before you saying i've decided
and so if
and so the claim is well if this
potential has predictive information of
your action and is the cause of your
action and it's happening prior to your
conscious decision your decision cannot
be the thing that caused the action
um
there's a there's a problem right away
with this in that with erp methods
you're actually averaging over many many
trials to get these waveforms because
you're measuring from the outside of the
brain it's like trying to detect like
events inside a stadium while measuring
like listening to the roar of the crowd
on the outside and
you're limited what you can do so you
have to average together a lot of
different um episodes and then you get
these event-related potentials or erps
and but
so you get predictive information from
this of when people moved but the idea
that a readiness potential is causal or
deterministic in some fashion there's
some debate about that whether you can
infer that
i'm going to say the readiness potential
is in fact reflecting
a causal process
and it's reflecting a conscious causal
process even
that is contributing to the action um
upstream of um the decision itself where
the decision could have some more
you know it depends i don't know if
there's one account but it could have
some epithelial aspects to it and that
the decision
is not necessarily um the thing
is it's not the only uh difference maker
there but the idea is that this
is a function of
mental imagery where you
are imagining
and as you're rehearsing moving your
hand
you're having different things
associated with it
and that building up
of that recurrent a building up of
activity in these body maps
whether we're talking about the getting
ready to actually change your
proprioceptive pose as you're imagining
starting to move closer to a threshold
where you're going to get robust enough
activity that is actually going to drive
your muscles and your effector systems
or building up of activity
in your
anteroceptive modalities like your
insular and cingulate hierarchies and
maybe their cross
maybe their synesthetic like cross
couplings with other modalities that
that building up of a feeling of urge is
itself consciousness leading to the
stream
the causal stream of action
so
that i would say so yeah the
and then on top of all the different
imaginings would be orchestrated by the
capital system would be the basic model
so
currently
and so and and
so currently i am working on
uh expanding this um to seeing what
different states of consciousness um the
ways in which they could impact these
sorts of phenomena um
in terms of
changing your awareness of this
rehearsal process
uh or changing uh
that'll be one of the primary uh
things of interest
and also whether differences in the
mechanisms of agency could potentially
contribute to the phenomenology of
psychedelics i'll try to explain what i
mean um
so here would be someone relatively
unaltered engaging in mental rehearsal
their minds started wandering off to
nature they're seeing a tree here's
imagination here's perception here more
vivid than imagination and they're just
sort of
imagining things imagining will i
move won't i move and then at a certain
point
imagination becomes vivid enough that
they can really see it happening
and at a certain point of uh
vividness of imaginings as a function of
this rehearsal um of will i move won't i
move you get enough build up of whether
we're on the implementation level we
might talk or mechanistic level we might
talk about recurrent activity in terms
of active inference on the functional
level we might talk about model evidence
but at a certain point you cross a
certain threshold leading to model
selection
of you altering your proprioceptive pose
and this becoming a self-fulfilling
prophecy through active inference you
then minimize the prediction error
between your imagination i am moving and
the and the action through reflex arcs
the way that um basically motor control
is thought or is thought to work in
active inference
and predictive processing
so the psychedelic angle would be
as someone is dosing with these
compounds their imagination becomes more
vivid
and they might show stronger ramping at
first and maybe greater awareness of
this patterns of mental stimulation
leading up to the action
it might get stronger
still as you
dose more and more
um
also greater coupling between
anteroceptive and proprioceptive
modalities increasing the gain on this
positive feedback between mental imagery
influence of urge and so in a way this
would be an enhancement of
willing
the willing aspect of agency as you move
up this dose response curve but then you
get to a certain level and you start to
get into this psychedelic regime where
your thought becomes
highly creative
and then your directed willing
might start to go down um potentially
the idea is you might
find other things competing for your
awareness
different creative uh
possibilities so you're now imagining
nature very vividly and this is
competing with you rehearsing will
i move or won't i move
and
[Music]
you directing
extremely high doses you might get and
compromise of these mechanisms of agency
of this conjoining of your enteroceptive
and your proprioceptive predictions of
your basically
of your stream of consciousness being
pulled along by value-driven policy
selection via sophisticated effect of
inference
um
so i think
so the reverse direction is this um in
terms of uh
this paradigm potentially informing
psychedelics could be that one source of
hallucinations or delusions or
um atypical um altered
uh consciousness and cognition would be
that if you take the basic mechanic
micro mechanics
of agency
and and you compromise that so you know
as you're
you're beginning to somewhat imagine an
action but
it's not well integrated into some
causal controlling you could come to
this anomalous inferences about what's
causing these basically um
the different um endogenous activity
your brain the different like uh
events that could lead to motor to motor
actions if these aren't being integrated
into a self-consistent coherent causal
unfolding
one of the ways that you could try to
make sense of this would be a
confabulation of something like a
hallucination and so this could
potentially
also explain some of psychedelic
phenomenology um and potentially um a
clinical neuropsychiatric phenology with
things like schizophrenia
as potentially being a function of
disrupted agency mechanisms so that's
currently the area of focus and
there's going to be a pre-print just
came out on that called
on the degrees of freedom worth having
psychedelics is a window for
understanding and expanding
uh
free will i believe that's what i called
it
a little bit
um also apologies if there's any
strange stream hiccups but could you
maybe unpack what the alien
or extraterrestrial was doing and how
does the confabulation relate to a
narrative understanding of action
so in this one
so
you know we're starting out just like
imagining your hand moving or imagining
being in nature
and then same here as the dose goes up
and it goes up and you might start to
get some more intense enteroceptive
sensation um
sensations uh the five ht2a receptors
which um heavily mediate the effects of
classic psychedelics uh they're they're
highly expressed in the interior insulin
the top of the anteroceptive hierarchy
and so
you keep going up
becomes
the sensations become more intense
imagination becomes closer to reality
and so here like
what i'm calling the heroic dose in this
extreme dose regimes
you're starting to get for instance like
your ownership of the actions are
starting to get undermined so here i'm
depicting
like you find your hand moving but
you're not accounting for your willing
of the move
being the thing you're not saying oh i
was rehearsing it and it felt this way
and that was part of the cause of
streaming into action you just found
yourself moving and so one way you could
make sense of this or confabulate around
this here is a hand like it's a feeling
of the hand pushing down on your hand
from without like just an example of a
potential confabulation or hallucination
someone might have
and this one here it's expanded and it's
this basically
someone it's not even your hand anymore
pressing it but an alien's pressing it
it's just an example of for instance um
so psychedelics they the classic
psychedelics will act in these five ht2a
receptors
they are heavily expressed
on these deep pyramidal neurons um of
quarter texas six layers uh the layer
five um well basically they're big
neurons that loop with the thalamus and
they let you form these broad
synchronous complexes which in
predictive processing are thought to
encode your beliefs some subset of which
would be your experience
and so if you increase the gain on these
uh the idea is that you might have
enhanced perceptual vividness but
because though you've done a radical
alteration to
um
of multiple kinds to like the normal
regime of processing in your mind you're
the normal ways you would model
even though you're experiencing things
intensely this would uh potentially be
of an atypical variety of experience and
so here it's the intense experience
the intense
perception at perception of the alien
it's a counter factual alien it's not
actually an alien uh but
that would that would be an example of
an anomalous inference you might make
and it has some um relation to what's
happening and the fact that maybe there
was some motor rehearsal going on but
you're not able to keep track of it and
so and here this is um you're actually
having phenomenal consciousness in each
of these moments
but you don't have conscious access
unless in these iterative moments of
experience
you can somehow get call backs
where um things can be contextualized
within uh some sort of causal unfolding
the claim would be that basically this
would be a way of separating out
phenomenal consciousness from conscious
access that there's things that can
happen as you're generating these quail
states
as estimates of what's happening of
system world system world system world
specifically your sensorium
as you think it is based on your current
engagement or in counter factual
circumstances
and that this that's the stream of
consciousness but that not all the
frames of experience
are accessible or rememberable and so
in this case here you know maybe there
was some rehearsal but you're not
keeping track of it
and then the the um the the best causal
account you were able to come up with
was that an alien made you do it and you
might have even forgotten that this was
you or maybe you do remember it but
would need probably some more
contextualization or not it's unclear
but yeah so that would be the basic idea
is that psychedelics would be increasing
consciousness level or the vividness of
your experience
but potentially undermining the
coherence in terms of causal unfoldings
or your usual priors by which you
structure the world um in the spirit of
um robin carrera harris and carl
firstens rebus model which i'm currently
discussing in the context of a broader
framework that i call albus
but yeah i don't know did that help at
all or
like
like yeah it also it reminded me of what
you said about the uh different levels
and their interdependence and mutual
constraints so it's like a sound is
heard and potentially in one state of
consciousness or mind or brain
it's 98 likely to be one thing and
option b and c are one percent
likelihood and so just goes forward with
as if option a like as if i'm in control
but then
some
things might happen where like that um
one percent chance that it is an alien
gets accepted and sort of passed forward
and then that might lead to the
experience through the generative model
of something that like
was a distributional so it's like a
change in
quantitative distributions that leads to
a qualitative change at increasingly
higher and categorical and semantic
experiential layers
beautifully said
i thought
and it would depend on your um cultural
priors so and whether we would call this
like a relaxed belief or a strength and
belief i'm not sure uh but you know for
instance
you might not be seeing in like if you
you know or
an indigenous people of south america
for instance um
you know depend they might not see an
alien it might be um related to
something having to do with their
spirituality and
their their whatever available myths you
have
um
would then go into basically this
interpretation your best guess which
is always wrong um sometimes useful but
your best guess of what's going on will
be different depending on um
you know what they would call the the
set in the setting but also where um
the setting is the broader cultural of
the sentence setting are also broader to
the culture
um
not everyone will be not everyone will
come to the inference of aliens probably
and actually that's that's been shown um
that that hallucinations are uh
culturally specific
yeah with which kinds of
extraterrestrial
morphologies are seen in relationship to
which are prevalent in the media and the
stories of a given region
i don't know all the details but one can
imagine
yeah like not everyone i mean like you
could like say like um
uh
maybe there is something about like gray
aliens which is like a little more
archetypal i don't know if i'd say this
but like uh
if you look at like the eigen dimensions
like morphological variation what's
relevant to us like
you're just like exaggerating many of
the dimensions
that would be relevant for us engaging
in inter-subjective modeling or modeling
of ourselves even for the sake of
control it's like hands like bigger
hands might be important um
where is like
an attentional
um
inference like where is this person
attending to where am i attending to so
you don't want to know the heads and the
eyes that's going to be really crucial
um yeah that's that's a far out story
but
you know there could be aspects of uh
that aren't just through the medium but
it's it's super interesting
and um uh yeah not not to go into alien
stream mode
but um thinking about a large headed
archetype with very large
dark eyes and the long fingers like
you're kind of hinting at
it's like
it's all pupil
it's all cortex
it doesn't have the strength but it has
a lot of nimbleness with its hands and
with its body
and so like that's like one archetype of
of cognitive
action
it i don't know and then what
maybe there's a blob and a shadow
there's like these different
archetypes different little characters
in this comic book of cognition
not that different from a child's
affordances too
right like they're not they're not
capable of like moving things around
much but it's like their intentional
actions are mostly like hand-eye
coordination
of like that's their purchase on the
world that's their grip
but you know for all this you know so
this is the current like
focus is how might psychedelics
inform our understanding of the micro
mechanics
of agency
um and how might the micromechanics of
agency inform our understanding of what
psychedelics are and that's currently uh
one of the things i'm focusing on and
about to
do some experiments on um at this center
for psychedelic consciousness science
i'm working out
at hopkins but the
uh
fundamentally upstream of this uh the
idea is that
these studies which purportedly um show
that there's no free will uh they show
no such thing uh it's very ambiguous
what they're showing and i believe if
you do an active inferential handling of
them uh you'll actually see that there
are several ways in which consciousness
is contributing to causal streams
leading to action uh which would be
having some of the varieties of free
will worth having um you know is it
arbitrary
degrees of free will no uh are there
some varieties of free will worth having
that we don't have like can you just
like fly all of a sudden that'd be nice
it'll be worthwhile uh we can't do that
either but if you want your beliefs and
desires to be able to
meaningfully said to be able to be said
to be
uh
meaningful efficient core screenings
maybe even maximally efficient core
screenings of what is happening i think
we do have that and i think you can find
this even within uh these labet
paradigms
if you didn't uh i think you still could
have many of the varieties of free will
worth having because you know many
people have criticized it saying like oh
just moving your hand
without a reason that's not really
agency that's not what we want from free
will we want like meaningful decisions
um
sure but i i think even though even
though for these even for these studies
um which people often will you know
trot out and say look
my brain made me do it even then i i
don't think it follows
that uh
they show that we um that our
consciousness is epiphenomenal um
through and through and i think active
inference basically shows some of the
particular ways that consciousness is
indeed causal even in these
circumstances and i think that's a very
big deal uh i i don't know how well it's
surviving the replication crisis but you
know there's plenty of studies uh
showing that uh some undesirable
consequences of people uh not believing
in their own free will or their own
agency uh whether or not that works i
think there is a kind of um
this face valid account
of this and that like kind of like um
dumbo's magic feather so like you know
this elephant uh and i'm taking this
from dan dennett uh from his book
freedom evolves but uh the elephant uh
has a feather that the crows told him uh
we'll help him fly and he had his big
ears and he used him to fly when he had
the feather and but it was because he
believed um whether or not um believing
in free will gives you free will
not believing you're a meaningful cause
that becomes true just by believing it
um
so uh you know i think it's some it's
quite dangerous
to take basically
something where we have
something precious something that
basically would empower us to pursue our
values
and to say based on
the set of studies and using the
authority of science telling people uh
that they are not meaningful causes i
think that's extremely pernicious um
and i think active inference can
there's already great work being done
like within like the neurophilosophy of
free will pushing back against us and i
think active inference can help uh
showing people what are the meaningful
degrees of freedom that they have um and
how can they be
preserved and expanded
wow very
interesting do you have any more slides
to go through or
may i ask some questions
uh no more slides uh
that was it
okay so um
those who are watching live please feel
free to ask a question otherwise i want
to
pick up near the beginning when you
spoke about finding oneself in a stream
of action
so what is happening
when we find ourselves in a stream of
action
and i i want to hear what you have to
say and then take this to some questions
about memory and free will but when we
are suddenly aware
like whoa i'm on a run i mean i guess i
did make prior decisions about deciding
and so on but like whoa now my leg is
moving forward
so the
i imagine this this varies a good amount
like as a in
in
pure and intra individual difference
variable so like both between and within
people you're going to need a good
amount of variance on this i think
but the way you know heidegger described
it in terms of this difference between
like describing like hammering and
you know when you're a skilled crafts
person uh it's the hammer is in your
hand and it is ready at hand and you're
you could your mind could be elsewhere
or people might have the phenomenology
of this like
on a run or on a drive
you might just find yourself home you
can listen to an audio book you'll
barely know you're just you have this
effortless mastery of the task set
and it's only when something goes wrong
that things are brought into awareness
and so
the
it's only and so then you get this
motion between so here's the hammer just
in your hand ready at hand to present
to him
and now it's in the foreground it was
initially in this um
unconscious or semi-conscious background
and so if someone's running like for
instance they could largely be in a
similar state of effortless mastery
especially because you know just natural
pendulum motion gets you like a lot of
the control um that combined with some
spinal pattern generators you know it's
and a little other tweaks it's like you
barely need to do anything once once
you've been trained up uh but
let's say you're trail running and or
let's say you run and then you step on
something
the idea would be that this violation of
your expectations uh would cause uh
basically prediction error
and that this prediction error the the
thing that was different so okay so
within predictive processing part of one
of this
targaryen phenomenology where things
just become unconscious
and you only become conscious when
you're um something's wrong you might
while being careful not to conflate
levels of analysis
you could get a good amount of this just
from predictive processing with the dual
tier architecture
like if
basically you're
really well trained up you can explain
things you can basically handle things
just with these efficient
unconscious couplings unconscious
inference
uh as a in a bunch of reflex arcs being
skillfully deployed doing most of the
things you need to do
uh
and whether you want to call this
modeling or not you know be a matter of
choice i would call it modeling
but you wouldn't need to become aware of
it
unless something was wrong and so then
the idea is this lower down it's not
handled you don't predict if you don't
explain away the prediction error it
makes its way deeper into the brain into
the
it becomes more broadly
uh
the deeper portions
of course
explicit modeling and conscious modeling
of
processing challenge
prediction errors will be greater
more capable of
accessing these richly connected sub
networks which could support basically
this larger scale integrative simulation
some aspect of which would be your
experience
i don't know if that got it at all but
yeah
awesome so
we're we're driving back towards free
will because i really liked how you
approached it in in this conversation so
i want to think about three
concepts memory free will
and experience
what are their venn diagrams like
can we
of things that we remember did we have
free will for them or not more or less
than expected for things that we
experience do we remember them more or
not could there be something that you
didn't experience but you remember and
had free will on and so on like how our
memory free will and experience bound
together
and that's a fantastic question i don't
so what's coming to mind
that's that that's a whole other
conversation though what's coming to
mind for me at the moment is um
that
there's a partial definitional
aspect of a connection between
free will and experience
and that what people so people want
different things i wouldn't call free
will one thing um in fact i actually
think there's a certain wisdom and just
like the language of it like people want
both like the the willing they want the
agency
and they want the degrees of freedom in
terms of they want to be able to pivot
they want to be able to
uh
have what they do be a function of their
past and being constrained by their
memories and their meanings from the
past
but they also want to be able to break
free
um whether in the face of something new
or just
encountering something new or to explore
and so um
having that that freedom for exploration
is also going to be a part of agency
both within a context and across time
but the memory is going to be important
because without the memory uh
that's the constraint based on values
based on you um
you know there's the many aspects of the
cell for instance uh some some of the
most essential ones and maybe some of
the the gold standards of free will some
frankfurt mesh theory afraid it was but
it's like this interface of like you
both want things and you want that you
want them where the wanting that you
want is based on this integrative and
like narrative type self
and so that would be a way in which
memory would very strongly like where
free will be a function both of
experience that you want your experience
your consciousness and your experience
to be part of the causal stream leading
to action
part of your your valuing your affective
inference you want that to be
influencing both across time and in the
moment
um and so the experience would be
essential like
it's not clear that many like dennis has
argued like that um the freewill
consciousness must always be handled
together um but and
without without memory um you also
though it's not you either i think
there's an interesting thing though um
in terms of like you're alluding to like
basically connections between causation
and memory uh and i believe we are
better capable of remembering things
when we can
take them up into a causal unfolding
this gives this this basically affords a
representation with a more of a sparse
structure of of salience of this led to
this led to this and then you hold that
causal graph in your mind and as
basically the core of your generative
model and it seems to be like a highly
efficient way of remembering things is
come up with a causal account of them
and so if something is a product of your
agency in a way that's that is all
automatically structuring things in this
causal set fashion and so there should
be a connection
between having agency and free will in a
circumstance and being better able to
remember things i don't know if that's
the case but um
it seems like some things from education
theory suggests like with respect to
active learning but
i could see that going a lot of
different ways um but
and so that's a deep question and those
that's that's what came to mind but like
what do you think
wow well the the last piece you brought
up about the
the sparsity
kind of the sharpness on the sparsity of
the causal story
and then things that have a sharp
and a sparse causal architecture as
experienced with our very limited
working memory
they're like pre-digested and therefore
very apt
to be able to
leave certain kinds of traces
and then maybe something could leave a
trace that didn't have a perceived
sparse causal architecture in the moment
but that might be like an example of a
memory that's hard to recall
or that might be like
cleaned up in post-production
and maybe very susceptible to being
influenced because like subsequent
updates could um
try to draw attention to part of that
uncertainty
and um like if there was just a loose
memory of many things happening at a
scene
asking even a question about part of it
could start to sharpen
that aspect
and
so it's
it's an interesting question and also
kind of like the questions like what if
you had some sort of suffering but you
didn't remember it
or in between moments or when you were
sleeping you were having some sort of
negative
experience
so just
i mean
what is happening with the
mind and the brain the the brain seems
to be
continuous
but then we have these
more flashes and discreteness
and shifting of mental attention
but
it's good
i just like the way you're describing
this um
uh
i feel like it's like like a really good
case in point of like the answer to do
we or don't we have free will should
always be what do you mean and and the
answer is always like um
like you like the way like you're
showing these different processes could
either go together synergistically or
come apart um
it's like
how many meaningful degrees of freedom
do we have and what circumstances or and
what senses do we have how much of which
of the degree varieties of free will
that we want in different circumstances
so it's like the answer is there isn't
their free will
um
it seems like like much more interesting
is getting into the details and useful
it's like getting into the details
you're talking about right now with like
the different ways that memory and
experience and choice can all
go together or not both within and
across
time
like that's
and then that answer is like that i
guess you could say that's like that's
the real problem of free will and then
that that
um interesting yeah like um that when
the experiment of pushing the button is
presented as being about the exertion of
decision making in the moment
rather than the um
memory or the recalling of something
that might have been different in the
moments
those are quite different
settings and it could be a total
different neurophysiology
so and also what you said about how
this sort of tension between having a
connection to the past and the
constraints that it provides but also
the ability to choose and i guess that's
what's explored in these varieties
papers so i wanted to
uh not just ask like what are the
varieties but just specifically asking
about the similarities and differences
with bodily action
what are the varieties of free will we
might have with respect to bodily action
like the so-called voluntary and
involuntary bodily processes and then
mental action
where in active inference we can model
regimes of attention and metacognition
and thought as like action policies on
mental states so what kinds of free will
are out there for the body
and what
does that say about what might be
a cognitive
degree of freedom or not like you know
just choosing what we want
so
in terms of like
body actions
if we're dealing with something highly
rehearsed
then it seems like
that could be an example or or
something where it's like
um
you can model that the predictive
processing like a hammer strike and the
loop is closed before it ever even
enters like the brain it's in the um
the
cn the cns and the reflex arc but
doesn't perhaps even make it up top
where your body moves that's just after
the fact that you're aware of it
but then if you're doing something
like uh
and so then like at this other extreme
of abstraction you might have something
like planning uh
reaching a distal goal where there's
many steps involved and you need to come
to some sort of sequence of the steps
and along the way
um actually i don't that'd be the
extreme but that would be
a little like
there's certain things that have to
happen in some ways like at the extreme
of abstraction it might be something
like uh going to grad school or
something like that or you know uh too
real winning a new job
two
ouch
um but like that itself there's a lot of
things that happen have happened before
other things a lot of dependencies and a
lot of multiple realizability like
there's always multiple realizability
like you know i go to reach for this
glass i could have reached for like this
i could have done a weird thing and gone
like this or like you know i could have
pinky out pinky n you know i prefer
pinky out um but like there's all sorts
of things that could have done there is
multiple realizable but the multiple
realizability of something like you know
going to college going to grad school
that's even more so like the number of
ways you can go into it and then i guess
i'm thinking like in this middle regime
of something that's still like very
clearly
metoric
but would be novel in that like um
fine-grained motor control like i'm
learning for the first time like i'm
doing a tea ceremony or i'm learning
a
calligraphy or i'm just learning to knit
or something like
there it's the fine-grained things
are now
being monitored um as uh present at hand
and and you actually need to use your
sophisticated inference machinery
to help
scaffold
this basically um
uh
the acquisition of skilled motor
abilities of skill the capacity for
skilled motor performance
but
i would also i think suggest that um
the whole way through
it's always built
um experience when when once it's being
co-opted or controlled in its
controllability
is always um modal in a motoric fashion
uh so one of the
uh claims i make in this paper
it um out that uh
it's called pre-motor theory but that
basically like uh through partial
expression
of a motor command or a motor prediction
the reference copy from that the
associated sensations can be used as a
means of top-down attentional selection
could be used as a means of attending to
memory in terms of working memory
basically you can use these
partially expressed motor predictions
not enough to actually cross threshold
but use them to basically as a source of
control
over dynamics um
of where your awareness is going and
what's going in and out of your
awareness and the claim i make is
actually that this is uh exhaustive like
this is the only like lever you have
is basically whatever is built off of a
control hierarchy off of skeletal muscle
it's a claim
but
the idea would be like even talk about
something as abstract as
you know going to college or grad school
there's still going to be
some so it has to cash
out as
attic and modal
uh
you're seeing yourself in the different
contexts even for the abstracts like the
most like justice
um you you still to experience it
it's still going to have some sort of
thing that you you know here's justice's
scales here's the courtroom here's
seeing this memory from your past where
there is an impulse or justice was
served here's you feeling this like
uneasiness or this like righteousness um
so
so the idea i would claim is that like
any kind of control on any level will
always cash out motorically
but there are meaningful differences in
terms of
um whether you're engaging with
something which is involving these
immediate fast feedback loops it might
be
multiply realizable but less so or
something which the um
affordance structure is more
being played out in terms of your
capacity to control it and relate to it
in terms of these
uh
even more multiply realizable high-level
plans of all the things situations you
might be in they'll be related to
achieving
high level
uh goals or abstract goals
um
i don't know if that makes sense
well one one thought on that is it's
like a jigsaw puzzle
so there's only one way to
assemble it and it's kind of like there
there's therefore this bundle of
trajectories of different realizations
of how one is going to assemble it like
there's sort of what happens on the
table all the combinatorics of the way
to assemble it and then there's like all
of the real-life combinatorics about how
many minutes am i gonna spend playing
this jigsaw and then i'm gonna go get up
and do other stuff and so the multiple
realization of the jigsaw where it does
all kind of come back to being completed
is one thing and then yeah you brought
up how when things are
even the outcomes are unknown or there's
multiple realizations
those are where
we start to maybe think about
hierarchical nesting of models like
we've been discussing in the slam paper
and also
the vivid imagining of different
future states
what is the
regime of attention
that might
for somebody who wants to be an athlete
help them make practicing and
being on that path like more natural so
what what how specific and what
modalities that's kind of what it made
me think of but
i i kind of want to keep on going on
this mental action route has there been
anything like a mental or a cognitive
libay experiment like where the
instructions would be like
take a couple of breaths and just you
know get up and walk around or whatever
just take a couple breaths
and then identify the moment on the
clock when you chose to think about x
a pure mental on mental
assessment
so
just before i forget i actually think
like the what you're just mentioning
like the optimal intentional engagement
for something like motor or something
like like a sport or some performance
actually that's like a key example of
like
through skilled mental action or not
through the skillfulness of your mental
actions having more or less freedom
where like for instance um
if you're choking for instance you do it
wrong um
june tony has a good paper on choking
and active inference and so if you get
that wrong that would be like your free
will being undermined by your
mental action not being uh well
calibrated in terms of where you're
positioning your intentional selection
for optimal grip or optimal engagement
with what you're doing
um
the
in terms of this pure like more purely
uh mental action the bed and the there's
a couple
there's different um versions of it that
have been run
uh some of which i think
would get a little bit
more to that um
and
kind of what you described in terms of
um uh
uri mouse has one paper called um
decisions like it's deciding or
decisions that matter and so basically
it would be choosing between charities
and so then you so
um
and then in this charity choice you
actually don't see this same type of
ramping and i think the support to some
degree um
the model i'm suggesting and that like
if this ramping is a buildup of
basically activity in your
action-oriented body maps
cross-coupling with your
interceptive body maps i mean this
feeling of urge and mental stimulation
it makes sense you would have that for
something like pressing a button but if
it's something like which charity i'm
going to donate to um you might not get
that same kind of tight coupling and
feedback and so i think that's some
evidence in support of that but i think
the particular thing you brought up
there's these um
this is a direction i'm uh looking in
beginning to look into there's these
closely related waveforms to the
readiness potential um the um
event-related negativity
and the um spn um
stimulus preceding negativity and i
believe so some of them would be for
instance um preparing for
information that's coming um and then
acting i think that would be the ern or
the spn the stimulus proceedings
you're preparing to receive information
that's
possibly salient but there's no action
required
so i think that might be potentially you
could think of all these things though
um
inactively as having they look
very similar electrophysiologically and
i would suggest that they are
all fundamentally similar and that what
they're using whether we're talking
about um
patterns of attentional selection or
specifically um orchestrating mental
stimulation to
act or not in terms of an overt action
in all these cases it is grounded in the
modalities and this is basically
understood implementationally as
recurrent activity in different places
of control hierarchy over body maps
or
in terms of
algorithmically and functionally an
accumulation of model evidence for
shifting your proprioceptive pose now
before an overt action but for talking
mental action similar story but if
partially ex but if
your
if the model evidence i guess would be a
slightly different model but it's
i if you if what you're imagining is
your own you're imagining your body
being in a different state that would
allow you to orient differently
um
to bias your sensors differently to move
your attention around differently to do
different precision weighting
but
you you don't imagine it vividly enough
that it will actually drive your spinal
reflex arcs and that but that this would
be what you would use even for
potential purely mental acts
it would still be
co-opting a control hierarchy off of
skeletal muscle and the reason i focus
on skeletal muscle is because you know
it's designed to have basically
large gross actions with low latency and
it's controllable and and and
the conditions for fine-grained control
are realized because you can actually
direct your sensors
using your effectors
um with a large-scale meaningful outcome
that can be causally modeled and tracked
and controlled and so then the idea is
that basically
um
vygotsky first expressed an idea like
this i think with respect to thought is
inner speech where first you learn how
to speak and then through partially
expressing your speech
you learn how to co-op this process for
a stream of thought um as inner speech
and then whether you want to say that
that exhaust thinking is a whole other
thing but inner speech would be part of
a significant part of thinking um but so
the idea is this is all
intentional mental operations whether
we're talking about
um shifting around
basically the the fine green adjustment
of an overt skilled motor act or guiding
your mental action with respect to
attention and mental imagery and
imaginings that in each case
um
you have the initial
affordance structure the initial control
levers established via
these overtly expressed behaviors and
couplings of the world which then later
by
partially expressing them
gives you something you can repurpose uh
for things like imaginative planning or
covert detention it's
or i would argue
any intentionally influenced mental
process
may be
ultimately
have its origins in this co-opting of
motor control
bold claim
hmm
okay
so what systems yes go ahead
i just said could be wrong
not financial advice not not
extraterrestrial advice hardly even
active
advice though it's very interesting um
what systems
rise to this capacity
and does their embodiment matter
so like there are insects with
tremendously reduced central nervous
systems
um one could imagine a uh computational
system that can engage in counter
factuals but it's only affordance or
embodiment is like one you know
morse code receiver or something like
that so what
systems
have this capacity and why
um so i i
definitely don't know the boundaries but
if i were to shoot from the hip on this
the idea would be
the handling would still be of this
computational neural phenomenology or
mario phenomenology but instead of
drawing brains
uh we would draw a different nervous
system or whatever the um
signaling
information processing system is we
would still give it this kind of
handling where there would be a
mechanism there would be a function
there would be some intermediate
algorithmic
mapping across these levels and then you
connect this to phenomenology and so if
in this phenomenology you're having
basically goal states being represented
and these and the representation of
these goal states um
is part
at that level you're also able to get an
account
of the guidance of action selection to
bring them about then you could say that
you have degrees of freedom in that way
so for talking about something like in
insects um they
uh you actually sent me a really
interesting paper recently about dual
systems thinking broadly construed um
including for insects
where
and this
it seems like you would need
at least a
um
a two-tier hierarchy
where this upper level
can
break free of immediate engagements with
the censorium
and where
this lower level would allow for your
couplings with the world and the
orchestration of
overt action selection
uh in terms of actually like sensory
motor cup into the world
and then a process which can basically
um
top of that hierarchically higher
that could
infer these state transitions but but
without them being expressed
and if you have that then you could do
the type of counter factual processing
that you would need for planning and
constructing causal models
um
it seems possible that insects might be
able to do this in terms of um for
instance like in that paper you sent uh
recently um
like
these like do this so the central
complex uh
has like a lot of these properties of
the hippocampal system um it's kind of
like it has properties of the
hippocampal system
and the thalamus
um
at the same time
but
and it's giving you like the salience
map
um
used for both orienting and moving uh
but that you also get these mushroom
bodies which are like the stratum which
would be basically helping with
moment-to-moment action selection
biasing it in a value driven direction
and so
uh in this paper you're getting like
this um
dual dual systems for control
one which seems to be more immediate and
reactive and the other seems to be
governed by slower processes and so it's
possible that something like this so
it's possible that this could give you
the ability to
do
sweeps
of possibilities
of counter factual inference where you
basically take the beginning of
expressing the motor command
so the insect is thinking i'm a
locomotive in that direction
um i i don't know the evidence well
enough to know if this is the case but
um
it could be
and then
so so for a like a rodent you'll see
these sweeps in the hippocampus of like
there's a maze and you'll see like
predictive of whether the mouse goes
left or right you'll see these place
fields representing different points in
space and in anticipation of this you'll
see these sweeps ahead of activity and
then where this sweep is most robust
that'll be the branch that like the
animal will go down we'll go down back
to the places
in theory you could do a similar thing
by other means uh maybe with some
homology even in the insect nervous
system
maybe you can even do it in an ant
colony if you're getting like an inner
attractor capable of aggregating
across all these different
finer grain couplings and
engaging in control but so basically
whatever has
uh or what the i i can't say
i'm not going to say sufficient but the
claim i'll make for necessity would be
some sort of
dual-tier architecture where the lower
level
gives you the couplings of the world and
the upper level
gives you
counter factual affordance
and integration uh
across uh these lower level potentially
segregated um
coupling processes
something like that could could do it
for you and so
could insects do it oh sure potentially
i don't know could the
uh insect colony do it maybe
the thing where i would place a
potential constraint
um
is
it seems like we might need an
architecture
to have properties where it could signal
fast enough
where these inferences of quickly enough
that it can stay on top of its evolving
action perception cycles so in terms of
its surfing uncertainty it's moving
through the world as couplings
the architecture whether we're talking
about a brain or some sort of
signaling across multiple individuals
like a hive mind
we wanted i think to be fast enough
to
have the estimates correspond to this
sparse
graph um what benjamin would call i
think independently controllable factors
of the world
and
a causal world model where you are an
agent within it
but it seems like you would need to have
the ability to model um independently
controllable factors and so you need a
signal signaling system that's fast
enough
to pull this off and so some sort of
small world network architecture would
be likely required where you have a
combination of
local modularity but then synergy
through having some central hub
and so if this could be pulled off by
the hive mind and if this can
orchestrate the overall swarm to do
things quickly enough to basically have
purchase
have the right grips on the world that
it can both inform and be informed by
its action perception cycles
then you could have an agency
architecture
which by some dimensions we might
describe in terms of free will
that dodged the question
before i respond what about just the
computational one what if it was a
computational one and it was it was
instantiating a digital twin a limited
um or comprehensive digital twin of
itself
i mean i personally think um the the
i feel like like an integrated
information theorist would say
absolutely not some people uh
within like active inference communities
would say uh no it has to be physically
realized
but i think something like a digital
twin or some sort of emulation um the
important thing for me is that the
um
there is a set of dependencies of
effective connectivity that could be
involving virtual processes and that if
you trace out the patterns of effective
connectivity of kinds not necessarily
physical necessarily like made of matter
that
if that is entailing the modeling of a
system and its relationships with the
world and where within that system world
model it has this kind of agentic
affordance
uh for me that counts but a lot of
people would disagree on that but for me
i think
you're trying to find the
maximally explanatory core screening and
sometimes that might be fine found at
the level of the virtual machine and not
in terms of the physical realization and
then that's actually the most meaningful
cause and then if you trace it out there
that's where you would look for it and
so that could be in a digital twin or uh
emulation but a lot of people would
disagree with that
so when you were talking about applying
this to the colony level i thought about
like the foraging behavior that's like
reaching out of the ground and grabbing
a seed and so that's like the enacted
foraging trip
and then
is there a counterfactual
i could be foraging or we could be
foraging at some different scale
underground uh on the other side of the
markov blanket of
the nest entrance
and then what if somebody were going to
be tracking the the elevation of a
forager and they'd be like well they go
up and down in the nest
but on the times where they make that
decision to forage they always go up 200
milliseconds before foraging
it's like well yeah that's where the
nest entrance is
so without
going into whether they have will or not
it's like
it's some kind of cognitive motor
integration
when the person hits the button
so then the way that you frame this as
being like not a trivial artifact in
fact
an interesting
outcome of aggregation of erps
across trials
it's like
how couldn't there be
a coherent
preamble
now i guess it doesn't if we're 30
seconds long
that would be a different setting
but then when we connected to the
specific
mechanisms by which they're
that do have to come together
in order for there to be
a coherent motor action
it's it's quite an interesting view and
i wonder how those who
have um interpreted it
in a very different way feel have you
spoken or asked to anyone who has a very
clear and
um
different interpretation of what this
potential means
i've been discussing it some with um
before i forget
i've been discussing some with them or a
good amount with um erimos and aaron
sugar
aaron sugar has
um
he has multiple
views but some of them do disagree and
so one of them is you in theory because
you're averaging across multiple trials
there is an interpretation of readiness
potentials as artifactual
um and it's possible that sometimes
you are dealing with an artifact of
measurement
and this is like an open question
but he's also uh for instance uh uh
very like he's he's testing out like the
the mental simulation view also
um another interesting hypothesis he has
is actually some of the evidence
accumulation is actually fast feedback
loops with
muscle spindles and actually
you're getting basically the the the
urge actually a lot of is actually in
the body itself uh but one interesting
thing before i forget is that these um
like
build up and then threshold crossing
i believe this you'll see across all
nervous systems where you get action
selection and i would wonder whether
this you know similarly similarly to me
saying like you know this isn't just
like a brain story
might we see
basically something like this if we're
looking at them i think you're active in
paper you talk about like stigmatic
coherence but through some sort of like
forgive me if i'm like butchering it but
like some sort of like measure of that
kind you might see something like
generalized action potentials for large
scale changes in
um
switching modes of the hive mind of the
colony uh i and while i'm just
speculating i actually also in terms of
multi-stage hierarchies um
i actually wonder whether um
the brains like for instance the resting
state networks of the brain maybe not
like there's different like
granularities and parcellations you can
be as much as 17 or or more if you
wanted but um there are some solutions
that are like maybe you know so seven
networks are most well known but there's
also like five network solutions
and i'm wondering if they're actually
universality classes for active
inferential agents that you'll actually
get something like homolog
of different western state networks in
their patterns of effective connectivity
so generalized wrestling state networks
generalized
empirical phenomena to like things like
readiness potentials
uh very uh
very speculative but that's uh that's
the i think we might
a few interesting things that makes me
think of and uh are we making
cognitive science
a creation in our own image if we talk
about the generalized hippocampus and
the general and so
to what extent are we or can we must we
generalize from our own action
perception loop
is uh
putting another umbrella
which the human mind is just a
realization of
and saying well the cognitive domain is
bigger than the human brain because it
includes the brain body and the extended
niche but also includes non-human
systems like if we want a cognitive
science that includes a thermometer or
something like that like a thermostat
is that a
is that a cope
because actually
that is still
the water that that model swims in is
still human and cognitive
like
i don't know but these are interesting
pieces i mean
it seems like
it seems like surely what you're
describing has to be the case and it's
like
and that's like both a good thing and a
bad thing where it's like we need
to be able to draw on
an analogy with something we understand
uh
like we're always like
we're usually making you know sense of
things in terms of other things and so
like your our own experience as this
base domain in order to give us some
purchase like
can we do it without it you could say
like first principles thinking but like
which first principles um
but then there's like all of the
like the baggage that could come like
the disallowed like if you're if it
seems like
we can't avoid doing that
maybe we could but if we want to but
then like we really need to be careful
to track the dis analogies
like
if we're saying generalized hippocampus
like okay wait wait wait what are the
dis analogies here what are the proper
unique properties that are present in
the target domain and not the base
domain of like the map the analogical
mapping you're doing or vice versa
yes yeah
that's fraught what you're describing
yeah
um
well i think a kind of closing
area just one point that i want to pick
up on i thought it was really powerful
what you
said about really the social
consequences and the personal
consequences
of interpretation of neurosciences and
in some ways even science communication
around empirical results
like
the idea that we could opt out to free
will
and that in a world where there's
limited degrees of freedom you might be
coerced into thinking you had free will
or not
but if there's any glimmer of free will
it can be used to
deny and deceive itself
so that
puts
research in this area
in
a different reflexive position
than
research on other systems so i guess
just
how do we
move forward here while drawing on the
specifics
and being respectful of basically the
past the present and the future
i mean for me i definitely have a lot of
um
uh soul soul in the game and that like
this is actually maybe the biggest thing
that
a couple things but this might have been
one of the biggest things that got me
into cognitive science was
a very long extended um freak out about
free will when i was younger where it
was just
i couldn't see how anything could be
mean i couldn't see how anything could
be meaningful without it
um i don't know if i still believe that
exactly but
um
for me it was it was very difficult to
not believe that there were like this
sort of all or nothing thinking about
free will and then going with the
nothing
um
dennett actually rescued me from that
with freedom evolves that his book but
uh there was a long time where it
seriously
bothered me and it had
real negative consequences in my life
um
the and i'm not alone in this i've
talked to others and they also feel that
way and um part of the way this is
coming up in the present work with um
psychedelics actually
is um so there's this study with um i'm
preparing for with creative
professionals who are suffering from
burnout
and
one
thing i'm wondering in terms of like
people can get burnt out from you know
multiple reasons
but
to the extent that this is continuous
with
burnout is continuous with
uh
depression or like feeling like you
don't have agency
in context where you want to have agency
um or or feeling like you don't have
that you know adequate control
uh
for something where it really matters
that you do
um
that seems like a good recipe for
burnout and it seems also like a decent
model for some forms of depression where
uh if you view yourself as not being
able to be a cause in the world if
you're not able to meaningfully work
towards your values
that could be very distressing i mean it
could also be a state of like a
quasi-buddhistic like blissful surrender
but
um
you know there's a question are we
flirting with nihilism there this
question uh and the other question is uh
you know is it even legitimate though to
be an eliminativist
on the self and on volition
and then just to say it's okay you're
not real your vision isn't real anyways
don't worry about it was that even a
legitimate intellectual move to begin
with i would argue it wasn't
um
so yeah i think this is the stakes here
for people sense of themselves
i believe they really matter and i
believe they have both social and
clinical
and social consequences existential
consequences for people
and i'm glad that uh there's this like
growing community of people in the
neural philosophy of free will who have
been doing a really great job pushing
against like some of these i believe
excessively inflationary views
and i believe that active inference
might be
a really valuable contribution to these
efforts in terms of providing formal
models and models that can go across
this marian neurophenomological stack
um or computational phenomenological
setup
and actually address these phenomena in
enough detail where not only do we feel
like
meaningfully satisfied where we
understand our own agency that we could
we could intervene
um and hopefully for the better
yeah just just some last thoughts on
that that's very
powerful and the
the mutual constraints and the
interdependencies of the different
levels like
it may come down to someone's genetic
sequence of a receptor or um some kind
of
binding affinity with a molecule but
then it could also be integrated in kind
of a full stack way
with
um
[Music]
talk or action or
changes to the niche
so it gives like a full stack yes and
way that's not
uh i think
a dead end it's more like a starting
state like if the computer weren't
working and then there was like the
hardware and there's the software but
then
moving beyond just that type of analogy
just very
powerful about burnout and about the
different cognitive ways that we might
get there and get into it and get out of
it and so it's like stoicism or whatever
plus preferences
because
it's not just the neutral stance it's
not just a descriptive stance on burnout
there's like a preference there so adam
if you have any other thoughts please
feel free
i guess a
quick thought
is if we're looking and this is like to
follow up on the um commentary saying
like these somewhat
buddhistic eliminativist framings of
um agency and i said like are they even
legitimate uh i i'm gonna argue um no
they're not uh and specifically um if
we're thinking of something like
modeling
the self
through time
as a high level controller
if you um engage in some sort of
practice whether it's discipline
meditation for a long period of times or
you've taken like a very high dose of
psychedelics and you've basically
collapsed the depth of your the temporal
depth and counterfactual richness of
your generative modeling
you will not find yourself there you
will be gone there will be no like you
to talk about and you might call this
something like hugo death
but then to say that there never was
a you process to begin with um i believe
that is actually illegitimate you've
basically used a search strategy
um that a priori should not have been
able to find the self
and then using that search strategy you
then concluded it didn't exist and um i
think that just doesn't work
so
um in this case
uh
you know the quote down and again uh
you know individuals
their narratives their persons
you know they're real patterns
and um
but they're also there's a reflexiveness
to it where
their own belief and their own reality
is an important part of their causal
significance
and so
um you know i think uh it would be good
to have some some nice debates with like
different members of the active
inference community who are more
deflationary on things like selves self
processes and agency
because ultimately i think this is a
thing where it's going to be like well
we should you know be respectful and
disagreements um
i think it really matters we get it
right to the extent we can
thank you adam for the excellent
presentation apologies for any internet
glitches that might have happened
we are a strange loop and this has been
a strange live stream
always good talking to you daniel
you